A Guide to the Randolph-Meikleham Family Papers 1833-1954
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Randolph-Meikleham Family Papers 1833-1954
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
4726-c
This collection consists of ca. 60 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, Box 316, Monticello, Charlottesville, Virginia, 22903, on August 11, 1976.
Scope and Content Information
This collection primarily concerns Dr. David Scott Meikleham, a Scottish surgeon who emigrated to the United States and married Septemia Ann Randolph in the 1840's.
The special value of the collection is the series of medical papers and case histories which it contains, compiled and written by Dr. Meikleham in the course of his career. He discusses such topics as the treatment of Bariola [sic], yellow fever, and morbid mucous membranes, and he gives detailed accounts of autopsies, amputation, and morphine poisioning treatments as well as a discussion of the use of arsenic for medical purposes. His writings convey a good impression of the state of the medical arts in the middle nineteenth century.
The balance of the collection consists of Dr. Meikleham's papers and correspondence, as well as other Randolph-Meikleham correspondence and genealogical material.
Organization
The correspondence is followed by Dr. Meikleham's professional papers and genealogical material in chronological order.
Contents List
- Copies of letters of recommendation written for Dr. D. S. Meikleham by Richard Miller, John MacFarlane, W. Auchincloss, John Burns, William Couper, Alex Panton 1833, 6 items
- Letters of recommendation written by Dr. William Couper for Dr. D. S. Meikleham 1833, 1 ALS and 1 copy
- Letter of recommendation written by Dr. Alex Panton for Dr. D. S. Meikleham 1833, 1 ALS and 1 copy
- Letter of recommendation written by Dr. M. Auchinshloss (Senior Surgeon, Glasgow Royal Infirmary) for Dr. D. S. Meikleham' 1837, 1 ALS
- Joseph T. Crawford to David Scott Meikleham, M.D. 1843, 1 ALS
- Dr. D. S. Meikleham to Sir Phillip Crampton 1844, 1 ALS
- Dr. D. S. Meikleham to subscribers of the New York Medical Intelligencer1845, 3 printed letters
- Dr. D. S. Meikleham to Messrs. Goodhue and Co. 1847, 1 ALS
- Draft of letter written by Dr. D. S. Meikleham 1847
- Cribson Shattlerv to Meiklehams re disposition of Miss Scott's estate 1876-1877, 5 LS
- William Meikleham to Harry (Meikleham) 1888, 1 ALS
- Katherine M. Morphy to Captain Harry Meikleham 1927, 1 copy
- Landon C. Bell to Mrs. James Morphy including an extract from Bell's "The Old Free State" 1927, 1 ALS
- Letter of appreciation to Dr. D. S. Meikleham from his friends in Havana n.d., 1 LS
- Copy, Dr. D. S. Meikleham's Medical Degree from the University of Glasgow with receipt for same from U.S. 1833
- Dr. D. S. Meikleham's personal account of his travels and medical history, 1833 to ca. 1841 n.d.
- Autopsy Report: Examination of the body of A. Ogden by Dr. D. S. Meikleham 1849
- Medical Discussion: Morbid Mucous Membranes by Dr. D. S. Meikleham n.d.
- M. Boudin on the use of arsenic in the cure of disease by Dr. D. S. Meikleham n.d.
- M. Chomel on the treatment of Bariola by Dr. D. S. Meikleham n.d.
- Description of a case of Morphine Poisoning n.d.
- Description of Leg Amputation by Dr. D. S. Meikleham n.d.
- Discussion of the Yellow Fever Symptoms Issue by Dr. D. S. Meikleham n.d.
- Medical Report: Examination of chest by Dr. D. S. Meikleham n.d.
- ca. 10 receipts for (newspaper) subscription written by Dr. D. S. Meikleham 1837-1838
- Receipt from Alice Meikleham to T. U. R. Meikleham 1877
- Notes, copies from a statement sent by Miss Meikleham by Landon C. Bell 1924
- Albemarle County Circuit Court notice informing heirs to the estate of Thomas J. Randolph that they are being sued for non-payment of taxes 1954
- Calendar with Randolph Family Genealogical material written on the back n.d.
- Randolph Family Genealogical materials n.d., 6 items
- Photograph of Septimia Ann Randolph Meikleham and three copies of a photograph of an unidentified person n.d.